<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Infonomics Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-05T19:32:43+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robin Gower]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open Data Business Models]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2013/03/01/open-data-business-models/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-01T19:16:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2013/03/01/open-data-business-models</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Data doesn&#8217;t make for a good tradable commodity, as discussed in a previous post on the <a href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/10/25/the-economics-of-open-data">Economics of Open Data</a>. Because of these market failures, there&#8217;s a strong business case for the public sector to open data.
But what about commercial business models for open data? This post explains why it&#8217;s not just the public sector who ought to pay attention to this opportunity.
The post is split into three topics: opening data that you own (why data assets are more valuable to you open), using open data (how to exploit your or someone else&#8217;s open data) and commercial models (how to get paid in the process).</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Opening your data</h2>

<p>Why should you open your data? Here are a few reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li>Network effects</li>
<li>Risk mitigation</li>
<li>Reputation</li>
<li>Attention</li>
</ul>


<h3>Network effects - Open is more exploitable</h3>

<p>There is a much greater potential for exploting data where more people have access. As a result your data will have greater value when it is open (to see how see below). Although you may have to share some of the pie with others, the overall pie (and so potentially your slice too) will be bigger.
This is particularly obvious for businesses who have ambitions for their data that are beyond their reach. It&#8217;s clear that small businesses may not be able to afford a dedicated resource for data manipulation or scientific analysis. It&#8217;s also true of larger organisations where the analysis is particularly complex and requires the skills of a specialist.
The notion of a network-effect actually goes a step further to argue that it&#8217;s impossible for any individual business to realise the full potential of their data internally. The data has value for each person that uses it, and in turn each use increases the value of the data. This is because data doesn&#8217;t hold a value <em>per se</em> - it&#8217;s value is only realised when data is interpreted with context as information (i.e. when a datum is combined with another datum). If the openness is reciprocal (share-alike) then your data will increase in value as it is shared and linked with other sources. You may even reasonably expect to have your data corrected, cleaned, and maintained (reducing the cost of ownership). There is also the possiblity of other businesses being able to extract value with niche customisations that you don&#8217;t have the interest (let alone the capacity or knowledge) to consider.
It should be apparent that this benefit is not guaranteed in all situations. If the pie doesn&#8217;t get any bigger then there may be little to gain from sharing it. The likelihood is that it may be very hard to predict all possible avenues for exploiting your data. Further it&#8217;s not certain, therefore that keeping data closed a precaution is prudent - it may turn out to be short-sighted&#8230;</p>

<h3>Risk mitigation - Open it or else</h3>

<p>If you don&#8217;t open it, your competitors will.
The value of information depends upon it revealing something novel. Since there are usually a variety of ways of answering a given question it&#8217;s likely that your data is not entirely unique (i.e. for every purpose, and every user). As a result you stand to be undermined by a competitor who is willing to offer alternative (although not necessarily completely substitutable) data at a lower price. Economic theory suggests that, in competitive markets, the price will equal the marginal cost of supply. Since the marginal cost of supplying data is effectively 0 (or at least very low), you may well find yourself undercut by an open data provider. You are only insulated from this risk to the extent that alternative sources are not perfect substitutes for your data from the perspective of your customers and markets.
Again, this risk is not certain. If you have the sole provider of a data source for which there are no direct substitutes then the probability of being undercut is lower. By exploiting this monopolistic position, however, you leave tremendous incentives for others to find imaginative alternatives to your offering. It may turn out that you&#8217;re not as unique as you&#8217;d assumed. Indeed there&#8217;s no guarantee that you&#8217;ll sustain the position of sole provider. Changing technology means that markets that were once protected by barriers to entry are now open to competition. If you are to operate an open data business model, however, and focus on a complementary service, then you are much more likely to cement your position as the default provider and retain your standing in the market&#8230;</p>

<h3>Reputation - Open is credible</h3>

<p>Opening data is a powerful means of being transparent. That transparency will make your propositions credibile by sending the signal that you have nothing to hide.
As has been particularly obvious in the food industry of late (for historians reading this blog in the next millenium we&#8217;re in the middle of a crisis about eating horse meat that was advertised as beef), the complexity of global supply chains bring risks because provenance is hard to establish. Open data presents a solution to this problem.
This has to be genuine. Releasing data under the pretense of openness and at the same time making it difficult for anyone to interpret the data will be recognised as a cynical gesture.</p>

<h3>Attention - Open is attractive</h3>

<p>Where data is opened in an easily accessible format with some guarantee that the openness will be sustained, it will gather a lot of attention. A captive audience is certainly a valuable asset. The traffic it generates may be more valuable than the data itself. The technical implementation must be thought through carefully if the attention is going to be captured/ channeled through this approach.</p>

<h2>Using Open Data</h2>

<p>There are a variety of ways to profit from open data. The line-between this categories is blurred. The general sequence is from data source to final use. Applications may include one or more steps.</p>

<ul>
<li>Enabling Infrastructural</li>
<li>Information Enrichment</li>
<li>Analysis and Consultancy</li>
<li>Application Development</li>
</ul>


<h3>Enabling Infrastructure</h3>

<p>Although open data ought to be free to access it may not be free to enable that access. There is a cost (and therefore a profit) associated with opening data. A business or a government agency who wishes to open their a data are customers in this regard. Thus there is a business opportunity in supplying services such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>Information architecture design - planning out the schema, ontology, or technical implementation details for open data (either as a service or as creation of an open meta-data asset);</li>
<li>Database - the technology that will hold the data;</li>
<li>Web hosting - the technology that will open-up access to the data;</li>
<li>Service/ Application layer - the technology that will make it (re)usable: Linked-open data, indexing services, user interfaces, APIs, integration gateways, data loaders etc (note that I&#8217;m thinking particularly of just the server-side &#8216;openning&#8217; bit here, not client-side applications of open data - that comes next!);</li>
<li>Advice on Licensing - the legal framework; and</li>
<li>Business Advice on Strategy - as per this post!</li>
</ul>


<h3>Information Enrichment</h3>

<p>As we have seen, data is valuable when presented in context as information. There is a value then, in enriching data by adding more data or context. Some ideas for what this might look like are shared below. The general distinction about enrichment I&#8217;ve made is that it stops short of being analysis (i.e. the output of enrichment is more open data, not conclusions or decisions - see the following section for that).
Enrichment services might include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Linking-open data sources (tying a dataset into the semantic web)</li>
<li>Quality assurance - providing an independent certification or compliance service (must be careful to consider who pays/ scrutinises for the sake of credibility)</li>
<li>Text analysis - information extraction (entity recognition, annotation)</li>
<li>Cleaning data - e.g. reconciling duplicates, ensuring consistency, identifying junk data, processing data so that it conforms with an objective standard)</li>
<li>Reformating - i.e. tranforming data so that it&#8217;s provided in a more useful (typically machine readable) format e.g. translating pdfs into csv, wrapping a database in an API</li>
</ul>


<h3>Analysis and Consultancy</h3>

<p>Open data can be a vital input into services designed to provide advice and support to decision makers. Beyond the simple fact that the information is free, there is a value in using a resource that is open because it is verifiable. That is to say, your analysis may be reproduced and checked. Notice that this doesn&#8217;t actually need to have happened for this to be of benefit, indeed the very possibility may be credible enough.
For the sake of completeness here are some examples of analytical services that might benefit from using open data sources:</p>

<ul>
<li>Consultancy/ Advice/ Decision support/ Insight</li>
<li>Policy Development/ Advocacy/ Lobbying</li>
<li>Statistical analysis and modelling</li>
<li>Presentation (data graphics/ visualisation, sonification, and interaction)</li>
<li>Scientific, Technical or Operational research (and product or process development)</li>
</ul>


<h3>Application Development</h3>

<p>Finally open data can be integrated into applications that provide value to consumers, businesses, government, or indeed other developers. Here open data is interpreted in a particular domain of interest to provide a service.</p>

<h2>Commercial models for Open Data</h2>

<p>So we&#8217;ve seen the value of openning data, and of using open data, but how can this value be translated into profit? Here I&#8217;ll present a few models:</p>

<ul>
<li>normal pricing</li>
<li>cross-subsidy</li>
<li>freemium</li>
<li>advertising</li>
<li>sponsorship</li>
<li>affiliation</li>
</ul>


<h3>Normal pricing</h3>

<p>The most obvious model is &#8216;normal&#8217; pricing. This bears stating as it&#8217;s not always apparent from listening to open data advocates! Just because the data is provided for free, it doesn&#8217;t mean that the services that apply this data must be provided for free. Your ability to charge for something will depend upon how costly it would be for another person (or business) to reproduce the application you&#8217;ve created.
Traditional pricing models are also part of&#8230;</p>

<h3>Cross-subsidy</h3>

<p>The idea here is that an open data proposition enhances the value of complementary services to the extent that those other services make enough extra profit to pay for the costs of openning the data. Clearly this is easiest where the organisation that decides to open the data is also the one generating profit from the service although it may be possible to design commercial arrangements for a payment between two organisations.
The inherent difficulty with this model is problem of quantifying the contribution of the open data to the complementary service. Since open data is untraded and thus there&#8217;s no price signal of value. While it may be possible to calculate the total value of network effects captured by a given organisation, it is particularly difficult to put a price on the risk avoidance or reputational benefits.</p>

<h3>Freemium</h3>

<p>Where the service is the provision of data itself it&#8217;s not possible to follow either of the first two models. As such an alternative is to segment the market - providing a basic level of &#8216;free&#8217; service and a premium level of &#8216;paid&#8217; service (essentially a cross-subsidy from the latter to the former). This can operate like a loss-leader. Typically the market is segmented according to the level of access provided (number or range of requests permitted or the speed of response). As the premium services begin to differ systematically from the core open data offering (e.g. training or consultancy) this pricing model begins to ressemble the cross-subsidy archetype.</p>

<h3>Advertising</h3>

<p>This is the most generally-applicable of the pricing models. Where a cross-subsidy cannot be established (perhaps because the difficulty agreeing a contract between the data opener and service vendor) it may be possible to pay for open data via advertising.</p>

<h3>Sponsorship</h3>

<p>If your data generates enough attention, people may be willing to pay you to include their content. Naturally this isn&#8217;t an obvious option for a start-up or un-tested service and it may be inappropriate for some data sets. For example: sponsored links on Twitter, Google Search and Reddit.</p>

<h3>Affiliation</h3>

<p>This is the reverse side of sponsorship where affiliates receive open data for free which they then process and redistribute in order to send attention back up the chain. For example: Amazon.</p>

<h2>Further information&#8230;</h2>

<p>If you want to find out more then you might like to check out these links:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/OpeningUp/open-data-conference-john-sheridan-open-data-as-an-operating-model">Open Data as an Operating Model</a> - John Sheridan explains how a linked-open-data approach enabled a mutually beneficial ecosystem around legislation.gov.uk. Check out slides 17, 24, and 33 in particular - they should you how the pieces fit together.</li>
<li><a href="http://chiefmartec.com/2010/01/7-business-models-for-linked-data/">7 Business Models for Linked Data</a> - Scott Brinker provides some far more catchy labels for these ideas than I have! <em>Data-layer ads</em>?!</li>
<li><a href="http://blog.ldodds.com/2010/01/10/thoughts-on-linked-data-business-models/">Thoughts on Linked Data Business Models</a> - Leigh Dodds provides some insights into how Scott&#8217;s ideas might be implemented and also comments on a motive I&#8217;ve overlooked here - philanthropy!</li>
<li><a href="http://www.scribd.com/doc/124951288/The-business-of-Open-Data-where-s-the-benefit">The Business of Open Data - Where&#8217;s the Benefit</a> and <a href="https://soundcloud.com/theodi/odi-fridays-the-business-of">the accompanying audio track</a> - Jeni Tenison provides a contrast of a few models (including the closed data case) with the help of Osterwalder&#8217;s Business Model Canvas.</li>
</ul>


<p>If that&#8217;s not enough then you might be interested in attending a workshop on the <a href="http://futureeverything.org/summit/conference/business-of-open-data-workshop/">Business of Open Data</a> that&#8217;s taking place as part of this year&#8217;s <a href="http://futureeverything.org/">Future Everything Summit of Ideas &amp; Digtial Invention</a>.</p>

<p>Indeed if you&#8217;re in Manchester why not pop along to the next <a href="http://opendatamanchester.org.uk/">Open Data Manchester</a>?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[9 Tools Every Information Analyst Should Have]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2013/01/30/9-tools-every-information-analyst-should-have/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-30T12:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2013/01/30/9-tools-every-information-analyst-should-have</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was interested to read Rebecca Murphey&#8217;s <a href="http://rmurphey.com/blog/2012/04/12/a-baseline-for-front-end-developers/">Baseline for Front End Developers</a>  in which the author realizes that she has begun to take for granted a basic set of tools of the trade. She presents &#8220;a few things that [she] wants to start expecting people to be familiar with, along with some resources you can use if you feel like you need to get up to speed&#8221;. I&#8217;d like to pay homage to that article and revise it in light of <em>the tools I believe are essential for an Information Analyst</em>. There is considerable overlap in the tools suggested although the application will differ.</p>

<!--more -->


<p><img src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/regular_expressions.png" title="Wait, forgot to escape a space.  Wheeeeee[taptaptap]eeeeee." alt="XKCD Regular Expressions Comic"></p>

<h2>GNU/ UNIX Command Line Tools</h2>

<p>These tools are especially powerful because they don&#8217;t require you to load the entire file into memory. This makes it possible to work with very large files efficiently.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>head</code>, <code>tail</code>, <code>less</code>, <code>cat</code> etc for looking at files</li>
<li><code>awk</code>, <code>sed</code>, and <code>tr</code> for processing and altering files</li>
<li><code>cut</code>, <code>paste</code>, and <code>join</code> again for editing and combining text files</li>
<li><code>sort</code> and <code>uniq</code></li>
<li><code>wc</code> for counting lines/ words/ characters</li>
<li><code>iconv</code> for converting between different encodings</li>
</ul>


<p>Some useful resources include:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://blog.sanctum.geek.nz/series/unix-as-ide/">Unix as an IDE</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/linux/library/l-textutils/index.html">Simplify data extraction using Linux text utilities</a></li>
<li><a href="http://tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/textproc.html">Text Processing Commands in the Advanced Bash-Scripting Guide</a></li>
<li><a href="http://funarg.nfshost.com/r2/notes/sed-return-comma.html">Replacing returns with commas in Sed</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/robbyrussell/oh-my-zsh">Oh my zsh</a> - zshell a replacement for bash</li>
</ul>


<h2>Regular Expressions</h2>

<p>Regexs are extremely powerful, if sometimes counter-intuitive. They are vital for defining patterns and replacements in text processing. Although some <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1732348/regex-match-open-tags-except-xhtml-self-contained-tags/1732454#1732454">debate</a> exists a to whether they should be used to parse structured formats like XHTML, they are certainly a vital tool.</p>

<p>Having said which, I find this quote pretty amusing!</p>

<blockquote><p>Some people, when confronted with a problem, think “I know, I&#8217;ll use regular expressions.” Now they have two problems.</p><footer><strong>Jamie Zawinski</strong> <cite><a href='http://regex.info/blog/2006-09-15/247'>Jeffrey Friedl&#8217;s Blog</a></cite></footer></blockquote>


<ul>
<li><a href="http://gskinner.com/RegExr/">RegExr</a> - Regex building and testing tool</li>
<li><a href="http://www.regexper.com/">Regexper</a> - visualisation tool</li>
<li><a href="http://www.regular-expressions.info/">Reference Docs</a></li>
<li>An example for <a href="http://www.softwareprojects.com/resources/programming/t-validate-a-credit-card-1682.html">validating credit card numbers</a> or <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/164994/187009">validating UK Postcodes</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>A Programming/ Scripting Language</h2>

<p>If nothing else, these provide the glue to connect different sections of your data pipeline. The incredible range of libraries avavailable to most scripting languages will make quick work of many common information processing tasks: parsing, spidering, <abbr title="Extraction, Translation, and Loading">ETL</abbr> etc. The choice of language is down to personal preference or compatibility with the team.
It should suffice to say that knowledge of a scripting language is necessary and I don&#8217;t feel the need to recommend a particular language. Having said which, I can&#8217;t resist saying that I prefer <code>ruby</code> but have dabbled in <code>perl</code> and <code>python</code>. I find the following ruby gems indispensible: <code>mechanize</code>, <code>nokogiri</code>, <code>fastercsv</code> (now <code>CSV</code> in the 1.9 standard library), and <code>json</code>. I&#8217;ve also been using <code>javascript</code> and node for scripting outside of the browser as asynchronous processing has proved to be very quick (if a little peculiar to code at first).</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://mislav.uniqpath.com/poignant-guide/book/chapter-1.html">Why The Lucky Stiff&#8217;s (poignant) Guide to Ruby</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.rubyist.net/~slagell/ruby/">A guide written by Matz (the original author of Ruby)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/styleguide/ruby">Github&#8217;s Ruby Style Guide</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ruby-toolbox.com/">Ruby Toolbox</a> - for finding and selecting gems</li>
<li>John Ressig&#8217;s <a href="http://ejohn.org/apps/learn/">Learning Advanced Javascript</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Text data files</h2>

<p>Probably the most basic technology used in information analysis, the flat file is the lowest common denominator. You can almost guarantee that everyone will be able to cope with <code>csv</code> files (even if they need to be translated before loading into another tool). The expressiveness and rigour of <code>XML</code> makes it another vital tool although it&#8217;s rapidly being superceded in bandwidth-conscious realm of http by the less verbose <code>json</code>.
Information analysts ought to be able to handle (read, understand, parse and translate) files in these all of formats even if they immediately convert them to a prefered type.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.delicious.com/redirect?url=http%3A//andrewjwelch.com/code/xslt/csv/csv-to-xml_v2.html">XSLT for CSV 2 XML</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.w3schools.com/xpath/xpath_syntax.asp">XPath Syntax</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.evagoras.com/2011/02/10/improving-an-xml-feed-display-through-css-and-xslt/">Improving an XML feed through CSS and XSLT</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.json.org/">JSON reference with links to parsers</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Relational Databases, SQL, and NoSQL</h2>

<p>This shouldn&#8217;t really come as a surprise to anyone. If you&#8217;re going to analyse information, you&#8217;re going to need to deal with databases. An analyst ought to be able to write <abbr title="Structured Query Language">SQL</abbr>, understand normalisation/ denormalisation, and possibly also have some knowledge of <abbr title="Object-Relational Mapping">ORM</abbr>. NoSQL databases are also useful when the data structure is better represented by document, graph or key:value structures (and where tables would be very sparse).</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://dev.mysql.com/">MySQL</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.nparikh.org/unix/mysql.php">MySQL Cheat Sheet</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.sqlite.org/">SQLite</a></li>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Database_normalization">database normalisation</a> and <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2008/07/maybe-normalizing-isnt-normal.html">denormalisation</a></li>
<li><a href="http://nosql-database.org/">NoSQL Guide</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.mongodb.org/">Mongodb</a> - document database</li>
<li><a href="http://www.neo4j.org/">Neo4j</a> - graph database</li>
<li><a href="http://couchdb.apache.org/">CouchDB</a> - json + map reduce + http</li>
</ul>


<h2>Statistical Library</h2>

<p>Unless you really want to code algorithms for every statistical process from scratch, you&#8217;re going to want to adopt and familiarise yourself with a statistical library. I would strongly recommend <code>GNU-R</code> although other options include <code>Stata</code>, <code>SPSS</code>, and <code>Matlab</code> etc. Of course there is probably a library available for your prefered programming language. <code>scipy</code> and <code>numpy</code> are very popular choices for <code>python</code>.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.r-project.org/">The R Project</a></li>
<li><a href="http://rseek.org">R Seek</a> - R-specific search engine</li>
<li><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/tags/r">R tag on Stackoverflow</a> (bonus: <a href="http://stats.stackexchange.com/">Cross Validated</a> - the stats-specific Stack Exchange Q&amp;A site)</li>
<li><a href="http://blog.revolutionanalytics.com/">Revolution Analytics Blog</a></li>
<li><a href="http://docs.ggplot2.org/current/">ggplot2</a></li>
<li><a href="gretl.sourceforge.net">gretl</a> - Gnu Regression, Econometrics and Time-series Library</li>
</ul>


<h2>Visualisation Framework</h2>

<p>Similarly you&#8217;ll probably want to use some sort of framework for generating visualisations. I&#8217;ve tried many and have found myself coming back to a few:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://d3js.org">d3 data driven documents</a> - A JavaScript library for manipulating documents based on data using HTML, SVG and CSS</li>
<li><a href="http://docs.ggplot2.org/current/">ggplot2</a> - the tool that usually attracts people to R; excellent for quickly sketching out data graphics</li>
<li><a href="http://processing.org">processing</a> - Processing is an electronic sketchbook for developing ideas - in Java and now Javascript too.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Report Templating</h2>

<p>Usually you&#8217;re going to want to place your analysis in context with some commentary. If you&#8217;re going to be repeating a given report - either in part or in full - they you stand to benefit greatly from using some form of template. Again this will depend upon your prefered programming languages. My favoured tools are listed below.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.stat.uni-muenchen.de/~leisch/Sweave/">Sweave</a> - R + Latex and <a href="http://rss.acs.unt.edu/Rdoc/library/odfWeave/html/odfWeave.html">Open Document Format</a>. I&#8217;ve not tried it yet but <a href="http://yihui.name/knitr/">Knitr</a> looks like it could be a useful package).</li>
<li><a href="http://haml.info/">HAML - HTML abstraction markup language</a> - very clear markup with indentation (so you don&#8217;t have to write out every tag twice), you&#8217;re able to use ruby inline.</li>
<li><a href="http://sass-lang.com">Sass - Syntactically Awesome Stylesheets</a> - an extension of CSS3, adding nested rules, variables, mixins, selector inheritance, and more.</li>
<li><a href="http://garann.github.com/template-chooser/">Javascript Template Engine Chooser</a></li>
<li><a href="http://d3js.org">d3 data driven documents</a> - for programmatically creating html from data</li>
</ul>


<h2>Version Management</h2>

<p>Version management is vital for tracking progress, making experimental branches in your work, and coordinating across teams. The clear leader in this regard is <a href="http://git-scm.com">git</a> and the amazing project hosting environment <a href="https://github.com/">github</a>. I&#8217;ve got in the habit of versioning everything - not just my code - but my home file configurations too.</p>

<h2>And the rest&#8230;</h2>

<p>This is just a quick list I wrote off the top of my head. What have I missed? What else do you use?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Information Failure is not a Business Case]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2013/01/16/information-failure-is-not-a-business-case/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-16T14:39:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2013/01/16/information-failure-is-not-a-business-case</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ignorance is no excuse.</p>

<p>Here I&#8217;m referring to a public sector business case - i.e. a rationale for intervention in the economy based upon market failure. Not a business model. Information failure may indeed be <a href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/news/blog/2012/11/13/open-for-business/">a valid business model for adding value in the private sector</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>It&#8217;s all too common to see ignorance being used as a rationale for a public project - &#8220;if only more people knew about X then society/ the economy would be improved&#8221;. If there are gains to trade available through better knowlege, then there are (rational) incentives for private individuals to learn. If X is a public sector project then this is actually marketing - justifiable on strategic grounds but not on the basis on market failure. If X is an intrinsically or publicly desirable course of action (e.g. not smoking) then the relevant market failure is actually the <strong>merit good</strong> case which is based on people having accurate information but choosing to ignore it - here again, information provision is actually a type of marketing.</p>

<p>The business case for information-based interventions should actually be based upon a different type of market failure: <strong>assymetric information</strong>. This occurs when either the buyer or seller knows more about the trade than the other. This can take the form of hidden information (you don&#8217;t know the used-car salesman is selling you a lemon) or hidden action (your insurance company doesn&#8217;t know whether you lock your door/ set the alarm every time you go out).  This imbalances leads to <strong>adverse selection</strong> (in the case of hidden information) or <strong>moral hazard</strong> (in the case of hidden action). Either way, the good quality products or services cannot be distinguished from the bad quality ones on the basis of price (the mechanism through which all markets operate).</p>

<p>Assymetric information is not simply solved by information provision. This market failure creates a business case for redressing the imbalance in information. It might include the creation of accreditation schemes or quality standards that, if credible, will buyers or sellers signal their quality or screen the quality of their trading partners.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pay for outcomes not activity]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/12/19/pay-for-outcomes-not-activity/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-19T20:37:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/12/19/pay-for-outcomes-not-activity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Commission outcomes not activity.</p>

<p>As part of my contribution to <a href="http://thecreativeexchange.org/">The Creative Exchange</a> I attended a workshop on Public Service Innovation and Democracy. Through the course of discussion we soon discovered that several attendees working in creative and service sectors experience a common problem with tendering - that the organisation running the procurement often has very fixed ideas about what they want to buy. There was general agreement that this tendency to be very specific didn&#8217;t leave much room for imagniation and innovation.</p>

<p>The outcome of our discussion was a proposal to explore a new approach to commissioning digital and creative services.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Here&#8217;s a quote from the terms of reference:</p>

<blockquote><p>The standard tendering model is not effective in the contemporary cultural and creative sector:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Premature-specification</strong>: The traditional model, with a specification of how or what should be delivered, is appropriate to homogenous services or goods where tenders must meet requirements that can be determined before the competitive procedure. Creative services, by contrast, are constrained if the method is defined in advance. Instead the commissioner should focus on explaining their aims and objectives and allow the competing suppliers to imagine and suggest what and how these should be delivered.</li>
<li><strong>Speculative work</strong>: procurement of creative services can involve requests for ideas, examples, or other forms of speculative work like open competitions. This involves considerable upfront investment from suppliers, the intellectual property rights for which cannot be protected. Indeed the award of a contract is not guaranteed overall (let alone to any given supplier). Suppliers are at a significant disadvantage in this commissioning model and the incentives for participation are weak.</li>
<li><strong>Risk-aversion</strong>: The priority in procurement is often to minimise risk rather than maximise value-for-money. This can lead to a bias towards larger established firms at the expense of SMEs and of innovation.</li>
<li><strong>Administrative-burden</strong>: public tenders often involve lengthy pre-qualification processes and masses of paperwork (often owing to risk aversion as above). This burden weighs disproportionately heavily on SMEs who may not have the resources to respond or for whom such requirements may be irrelevant (i.e. a freelance designer working from her kitchen probably doesn’t need ISO compliant Health and Safety policy).</li>
</ul>


<p><cite>Alpha Procurement Proposal</cite></p></blockquote>

<p>The project is at a very early stage but I&#8217;ll provide an update once we&#8217;re underway.</p>

<p>If you&#8217;ve any thoughts by all means let us know in the comments&#8230;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3 Metrics for Heath Economics Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/12/19/3-metrics-for-heath-economics-analysis/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:43:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/12/19/3-metrics-for-heath-economics-analysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m often asked to suggest measures for assessing health interventions from an economic perspective. Here are explanations of four commonly used analytical methods:</p>

<ul>
<li>Reduction in Costs of Treatment</li>
<li>Cost per Quality Adjusted Life Years (QALY)</li>
<li>Incremental Cost Effectiveness Ratio (ICER)</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p>As should be obvious from the titles, cost plays a significance role in health economics analysis. The first measure considers cost directly. The second measures also incorporate utility or benefit. The final measure should be used for interpretation.</p>

<p>In practice, it&#8217;s advisable to consider using more than one method to account for the limitations of individual measures. It&#8217;s also important to control for demographic and socio-economic characteristics such as age, gender, ethnicity, employment, and health condition. It will also be insightful to consider location as a proxy indicator for a range of (highly-correlated) socio-economic characteristics.</p>

<h2>Reduction in costs of treatment</h2>

<p>This is the most easily understandable economic impact of health interventions. If preventive steps are taken, fewer people contract disease, and less will need to be spent on treatment. The main focus of research under this measure is in <strong>quantifying the intervention&#8217;s impact on health and the cost of treatment that is obviated</strong>. Weight loss, for example, will reduce the relative risk of diabetes and cardio-vascual disease. The relationship between intervention and disease risk might be established by reference to physiological measures (such as Body Mass Index). Cost of treatment might include the cost of prescription medicine, GP consultation, surgery and palliative care.</p>

<p>The difficulty with this sort of measure is that the impact is stated in terms of money that would otherwise have had to be spent and, as such, is quite intangigble.</p>

<h2>Cost per QALY</h2>

<p>A quality adjusted-life year, or QALY, represents <strong>the number of years of life that would be added by an intervention, taking into account the quality of those years</strong>. If the extra years would not be lived in full health they are given a value less than 1. Clearly the method of adjustment for quality is critical to this metric.
A commonly adopted measure is the <a href="http://www.euroqol.org/">EQ-5D</a> scale which seeks to categorise health states according to 5 dimensions: mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/ discomfort and anxiety/ depression. This is combined with a quantiative measure of the patients self-assessment of their health on a <em>vertical analogue scale</em>.
Other approaches include the <em>time trade-off</em>, where respondents are asked to choose between remaining in an ill state or being restored to perfect health with a shorter life expectancy, and <em>standard gamble</em> where the alternative could restore them to perfect health or kill them.
This measure is criticised due to the difficulty of establishing a meaningful, objective, and comparable definition of &#8220;perfect health&#8221; and &#8220;disease burden&#8221;.</p>

<h2>Incremental Cost-Effectiveness Ratio</h2>

<p>This ratio is used for comparing intervention options on a like for like basis. The Incremental Cost Effectiveness Ratio (ICER) is a <strong>comparison of the relative cost per QALY of the intervention and a reference case</strong> as follows (where QALY refers to a Quality Adjusted Life Year):
$$
ICER = \frac{ \text{£ Cost of intervention} - \text{£ Cost of reference case} } { \text{QALY Effect of intervention} –  \text{QALY Effect of reference case} }
$$
The ICER assumes a multiplicative model for QALYs (i.e. a change in scale will change the ICER ratio even though original figures remain the same).
Benchmarking against other interventions provides valuable contextual information. The <a href="https://research.tufts-nemc.org/cear4/default.aspx">Tufts Cost-Effectiveness Analysis Registry</a> is a valuable resource in this regard.</p>

<script type="text/javascript"
  src="http://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML">
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modest Evaluation and the Burden of Proof]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/12/11/evaluation-and-the-burden-of-proof/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/12/11/evaluation-and-the-burden-of-proof</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Impact evaluation studies are often called upon to put a price on something that is impossible to value. Evaluators ought to take this limitation seriously when designing their research methods. This post discusses the problem and suggests some responses.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The <strong>burden of proof</strong> is said to lie with the party making a claim. In order to convince someone of some truth, you are obliged to support your claim with evidence. The audience hearing your claim will make a judgement by scrutinising the evidence you present in support.</p>

<p>This obligation should not be treated lightly. In some cases, it isn&#8217;t possible to marshall evidence to support our intuitions. Indeed we can&#8217;t always know what we don&#8217;t know and so we shouldn&#8217;t act like we can. Recognition of this limitation is known as <strong>epistemological modesty</strong>. This perspective doesn&#8217;t mean that we have to admit defeat. Instead it is basis for action. Action that takes place with an awareness of our necessarily limited understanding.</p>

<p>This approach has important lessons for evaluation. It suggests that we should avoid the temptation to reduce the nuances of impact evaluation to a single result (i.e. an absolute figure in pounds sterling for the overall impact or a summary cost-benefit ratio). Although it might seem appealing to be able to boast about a large absolute impact figure or to point to a high return on investment, the evidence required to support those definite figures may not be credible. We should not invite the audience to question and undermine the claims being made. Instead we ought to make modest claims that allow for the greatest degree of flexibility over the evidence. <strong>It&#8217;s better to be confident in a modest conclusion than unconfident in a bold one</strong>. Our efforts should be focussed on validating our assumptions and understanding situations under which our conclusions might be undermined. Thus the burden of proof is lightened and the claims more credibile.</p>

<p>Our ability to do this will, of course, depend upon the circumstance but examples of how this might work in practice include:</p>

<ul>
<li>establishing the minimum level of evidence required to demonstrate that benefits are at least equal to costs (rather than straining evidence to calculate the maximum plausible ratio of benefits to costs),</li>
<li>comparing projects on the basis of the credibility of the evidence required to demonstrate that break-even position,</li>
<li>deriving relative rather than absolute measures (so that we be certain that the comparisons are fair and reasonable,)</li>
<li>using confidence-intervals rather than point-estimates to make inferences, and</li>
<li>using evaluation to guide research (to identify otherwise implicit assumptions that need to be validated).</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is Infonomics?]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/12/06/what-is-infonomics/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-06T12:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/12/06/what-is-infonomics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I started my <a href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk">economic consultancy and information analysis business</a> back in 2007 I was searching for a name that would describe my work in economics and information analysis and that was unique enough to appear early on in the search enginge result pages without too much trouble. At that time is was still cool to use a portmanteau (this was before dropping out a vowel caught-on) so I was certain that I was on to a winner.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I didn&#8217;t realise for some time that the term had already been coined by Doug Laney, then at META Group, to describe the practice of treating information as an asset. As an intangible asset information is given a price, appears on financial accounts, and is managed accordingly.</p>

<p>Since this definition now seems to dominate the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Infonomics">wikipedia page</a> on the subject, I think it&#8217;s about time I added my voice to the debate.</p>

<p>In my mind, at least, <strong>Infonomics is about information-based on economics, not economics-based on information</strong>. Whereas econometrics refers to economic statistics (and, let&#8217;s be honest, principally regression analysis), I imagined Infonomics as a super-set including elements of computer science (such as information theory, algorithmic design, artificial intelligence, and data visualisation).</p>

<p>Of course there&#8217;s rarely a single, unambigious definition of a neologism. But at least we can all agree that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Infonomics&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=471082260">wikipedia should no longer say</a> &#8220;nobody has as yet referred to himself/herself as an infonomist&#8221;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Questions to Consider Before Commissioning an Evaluation]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/12/05/questions-to-consider-before-commissioning-an-evaluation/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-05T10:50:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/12/05/questions-to-consider-before-commissioning-an-evaluation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Planning is fundamental to successful evaluation. Considering these questions will help you to understand what you need to discuss with a contractor so that they can design an evaluation effectively.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What is the objective?</h2>

<p>This ought to be defined in terms of the key questions that the evaluation ought to answer. The choice of question will determine which methods are used and what data is gathered.
Typical objectives include wanting to:</p>

<ul>
<li>have evidence to attract funding or investment</li>
<li>identify what has worked and what hasn&#8217;t to make improvements</li>
<li>share lessons learned with partners</li>
<li>build plan for future activity</li>
</ul>


<p>Clearly a different approach to evaluation would be required to answer each of these questions.</p>

<p>In order to define the key evaluation question(s) it might be useful to consider:</p>

<ul>
<li>Who is the audience is for the evaluation (your board of directors, external funders, or participants)?</li>
<li>What will you do with the evaluation once it&#8217;s complete?</li>
<li>What decisions will the evaluation help you make?</li>
</ul>


<h2>Who are your stakeholders or beneficiaries?</h2>

<p>Different people will value your work for different reasons. Those reasons won&#8217;t always overlap and may even conflict. The evaluation might reach a different conclusion based upon the perspective you take. Answering this question will help you to determine scope and focus - indeed it&#8217;s sometimes useful to think about the maximum possible range of beneficiaries just so that you can determine those whom won&#8217;t be considered.</p>

<p>Thinking about stakeholders will also help with the preceding question. Often the stakeholder may also be a funder. It&#8217;s important in these cases to have the relevant people involved in the evaluation from the outset. This means discussing the objectives and proposed methods with them. Not only will this give your conclusions greater credibility with the target audience, but it will also help to ensure relevance. Further, they might be able to offer insight or resources from other work they&#8217;ve seen.</p>

<h2>What can we do internally, where do we need support?</h2>

<p>You can expect good evaluation to cost at least 10% of the operating costs of the service being evaluated. It not necessary to outsource all of the evaluation work. Even where you are contractually obliged to appoint an independent consultant it is still possible for you to be involved.</p>

<p>External support will typically be need for technical aspects such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>establish a research methodology or epsitemological framework for answering your key evaluation questions</li>
<li>designing primary research (sampling, questionnaires, or topic guides)</li>
<li>devising and analysing statistical models to establish behavioural change, causal effects or to financial proxies for non-traded costs and benefits</li>
</ul>


<p>Whereas internal work might focus on activities like collecting monitoring data.</p>

<p>As discussed above, it is vital that internal staff are involved in the conversations with stakeholders if the evaluation is going to be useful in future.</p>

<h2>Do we understand the evaluation design?</h2>

<p>In order to interpret the results of the evaluation it will be vital for you to understand how those results were reached. This doesn&#8217;t necessarily mean, for example, that you need to know how to calculate a &#8220;two-stage Heckit regression&#8221;. You do at least need to know why this method was used (i.e. in response to selection bias) so that you know that the findings do account for the fact that sample of people consulted was biased. This is important for forming your own judgements about the results and for dealing with criticisms from others.</p>

<p>A empirically flawless method is useless if none of your audience can make sense of the results. That&#8217;s not to say that you should avoid technical research methods; indeed this question might be better phrased as: what do we need to learn to understand the evaluation design?</p>

<h2>What data do we already have?</h2>

<p>Having data available may help to save on the costs of data collection. Data can come from obvious sources such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>the monitoring data you&#8217;re contractually obliged to collect,</li>
<li>management information you use to direct your work, or</li>
<li>feedback forms you&#8217;ve used to ongoing service development.</li>
</ul>


<p>Data can also come from unexpected places like:</p>

<ul>
<li>administrative databases,</li>
<li>server access records or log files, and</li>
<li>email address books or messages.</li>
</ul>


<p>You should also expect to provide evaluators with:</p>

<ul>
<li>contact information for consultees - at the strategic and beneficiary level,</li>
<li>background information (particularly any work done to scope, appraise, design or commission your service), and</li>
<li>contractual and financial records.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open For Business]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/11/13/open-for-business/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-13T13:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/11/13/open-for-business</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post outlines some business considerations for open source. It follows <a href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/../portfolio_project/14">advice Infonomics provided to the World Wildlife Fund</a> in collaboration with <a href="http://www.ribble-consultants.co.uk">Ribble Consultants</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Open Source Definitions</h2>

<p>The term <em>open source</em> denotes software for which the original source code is made available and may be redistributed with or without modification. In practice this is typically coupled with a peer-production development model although code can be open-sourced without providing any means of re-integrated changes back into the code base.
Note that:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Free software is not necessarily open-source (closed-source software may be free)</strong>.  <a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/selling.html">Here ‘free’ refers to the freedom (to run, modify, and redistribute) not the price</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Open-source software is not necessarily free of charge</strong>.  There are a variety of business models for generating revenue from an open-source project including: ‘freemium’ (premium features must be paid for), consulting (selling services related to the product), support (paid-for training), subscriptions (original is free, updates require a fee), proprietary add-ons (fees for implementing/ developing bespoke features), and dual licenses (whereby only those earning money from the tool must pay).</li>
<li><strong>Open-sourcing does not necessarily involve any loss of control over the quality or integrity of the product</strong> (or intellectual property); multiple versions (internal and external) may exist concurrently.  Typically derivatives and modifications are made upon ‘forked’ copies (or branches).  The lead maintainer (person managing the code) takes responsibility for the core (trunk) version.  Changes contributed by the community (in branches) may be applied (used to patch) the original (trunk) or they may be pursued independently.  Moreover forks may pursue entirely different objectives without ever being integrated (e.g. a version is developed for a different software platform or only small portions of the code taken for use elsewhere).  See below for some real-world examples.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Advantages and Disadvantages</h2>

<p>The advantages of open source include:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Bug/ defect correction</strong>: with more people exploring and testing the code there is a greater chance that problems will be identified and solved (improving stability and reliability);</li>
<li><strong>Improvements/ new feature</strong>: there are more people to contribute ideas and code to enhance the product and integrate it with other developments;</li>
<li><strong>Credibility</strong>: greater transparency lends credibility (‘auditability’) and the product’s sustainability depends less on the original developer.
The disadvantages include:</li>
<li><strong>Price ceiling</strong>: the original developer may not be able to charge as much for software licenses.  We might expect that the fee could be no greater than is the cost of deploying/ implementing/ maintaining the code that is provided.</li>
<li><strong>Intellectual property</strong>: other developers may be able to implement competing versions (this is typically dealt with via licensing restrictions).</li>
</ul>


<h2>Open Source Business Models</h2>

<p>The table below describes how some of the larger businesses make money while releasing open-source versions of their software.
Typically there is:</p>

<ul>
<li>a distinction between a limited-spec version which is released open-source and a fully-featured version which is sold commercially; and/ or</li>
<li>a fundamental division of functionality along the lines of free to use, pay to develop/ sell;</li>
<li>a set of complementary services that are provided at a fee (training, support, consultancy).</li>
</ul>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th> Company          </th>
<th> Open Source                                                                              </th>
<th> Commercial                                                                 </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Adobe            </td>
<td> Flex platform for rich internet applications                                             </td>
<td> Flash Builder integrated development environment</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Apple            </td>
<td> Darwin: core unix compatible operating system released under Apple Public Source License </td>
<td> Mac OSX, Apple TV, iOS (iPhone/ iPad/ iPod platform)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Canonical        </td>
<td> Ubuntu: linux operating system                                                           </td>
<td> Technical support contracts </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Mozilla          </td>
<td> Firefox: web browser                                                                     </td>
<td> Partnership with google and others for including search engines in Firefox</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> MySQL            </td>
<td> Database: community edition                                                              </td>
<td> Enterprise/ Cluster editions, training and consultancy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> Sun Microsystems </td>
<td> Open Office: office productivity suite                                                   </td>
<td> Star Office</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<h2>What to consider before going Open Source</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Release the code</strong>: the source will be made available online (i.e. the code not necessarily the data)</li>
<li><strong>Release data</strong>: some example data may be provided</li>
<li><strong>Provide facility for commits</strong>: developers may ‘commit’ changes or ‘fork’ new versions of the software (otherwise developers are responsible for maintain their own – external – versions)</li>
<li><strong>Allow derivative works</strong>: software developed from the tool can be sold commercially (there may be dual licenses – i.e. one for users and another for re-sellers)</li>
<li><strong>Modifications must distribute source</strong>: Licensee must include the source with any modifications (i.e. cannot create a closed-source derivative)</li>
<li><strong>Derivatives subject to same license (copy-left)</strong>: require that the same rights be preserved in modified versions</li>
<li><strong>Provide user support</strong>: for example, via training courses/ email/ telephone/ issue tracking/ webchat to end-users</li>
<li><strong>Provide development support</strong>: as above but for developers</li>
<li><strong>Facility for community discussions</strong>: a popular alternative to one-to-one support, this allows users to guide one-another (typically moderated by trust users or employees)</li>
<li><strong>What aspects are free of charge?</strong></li>
<li><strong>What aspects require a fee?</strong></li>
</ul>


<h2>Comparison of Open Source Licenses</h2>

<p>The decicions you reach on the above considerations will help to determine which license is most suitable.</p>

<table>
 <tr>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>License</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>Attribution</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>Non-Commercial</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>Registration</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>Distribution</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>Combinations</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>Transformation</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>Linking</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>Copyleft</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>&nbsp;</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>&nbsp;</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>&nbsp;</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>&nbsp;</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>Licensee must include the source with any
  modifications</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>with other code</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>edit/ rewrite</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>with code under different license</span></p>
  </td>
  <td>
  <p align="center"><span>Derivates subject to same license</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td nowrap valign="bottom">
  <p><span>All-rights-reserved</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap>
  <p align="center"><span>n/a</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap>
  <p align="center"><span>n/a</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap>
  <p align="center"><span>n/a</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap>
  <p align="center"><span>n/a</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap>
  <p align="center"><span>n/a</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap>
  <p align="center"><span>n/a</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap>
  <p align="center"><span>n/a</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap>
  <p align="center"><span>n/a</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td nowrap valign="bottom">
  <p><span>Public-domain</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Allowed</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Allowed</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td nowrap valign="bottom">
  <a href="http://three.org/openart/license/"><p><span>Open-art</span></p></a>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FFFFBF">
  <p align="center"><span>Share alike</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FFFFBF">
  <p align="center"><span>Share alike</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td nowrap valign="bottom">
  <a href="www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html"><p><span><acronym title="General Public License">GPL</acronym></span></p></a>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FFFFBF">
  <p align="center"><span>Share alike</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FFFFBF">
  <p align="center"><span>Share alike</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td nowrap valign="bottom">
  <a href="www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html"><p><span><acronym title="Lesser General Public License">LGPL</acronym></span></p></a>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Allowed</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FFFFBF">
  <p align="center"><span>Share alike</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td nowrap valign="bottom">
  <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0.html"><p><span>Apache 2.0</span></p></a>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Allowed</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Allowed</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td nowrap valign="bottom">
  <a href="http://www.linfo.org/bsdlicense.html"><p><span><acronym title="Berkley Software Distribution">BSD</acronym></span></p></a>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Allowed</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Allowed</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td nowrap valign="bottom">
  <a href="mit-license.org"><p><span><acronym title="Massachusetts Institute of Technology">MIT<acronym></span></p></a>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Allowed</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Allowed</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td nowrap valign="bottom">
  <a href="creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><p><span><acronym title="Creative Commons Attribution">CC by</acronym></span></p></a>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Allowed</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Allowed</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td nowrap valign="bottom">
  <a href="creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0"><p><span><acronym title="Creative Commons Attribution ShareAlike">CC by-sa</acronym></span></p></a>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FFFFBF">
  <p align="center"><span>Share alike</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FFFFBF">
  <p align="center"><span>Share alike</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <td nowrap valign="bottom">
  <a href="creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0"><p><span><acronym title="Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commerical No-Derivatives">CC by-nc-nd</acronym></span></p></a>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #91CF60">
  <p align="center"><span>Yes</span></p>
  </td>
  <td nowrap style="background: #FC8D59">
  <p align="center"><span>No</span></p>
  </td>
 </tr>
</table>


<p>The GPL and LGPL Version 3 prohibits DRM, locked-down firmware, and patent lawsuits.</p>

<p>The BSD license prohibits the use of copyright holder&#8217;s name for promotion.</p>

<p>The Apache license requires that every file must contain all information about changes, copyrights and patent protection.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://osrc.blackducksoftware.com/data/licenses/#top20">Black Duck Knowledge Base</a> suggests that GPL2 is the most popular choice.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Economics of Open Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/10/25/the-economics-of-open-data/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-25T15:35:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2012/10/25/the-economics-of-open-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Data doesn&#8217;t make for a very good tradable commodity. Technological changes that allow us to connect and share data more easily are disrupting established business models. Therefore the public sector has a critical role to intervene in the data market and the private sector must adapt to ensure long-term sustainability.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The Market Isn&#8217;t Always Perfect</h2>

<p>Economists use this term to describe situations where the allocation of goods and services by the free market is inefficient (i.e. someone can be made better off without making another worse off). <strong>In some extreme cases the good or service would not be available without intervention by government</strong>. The market is only effective if the good or service:</p>

<ul>
<li>has a price which reflects all costs and benefits</li>
<li>can be withheld from people at reasonable expense</li>
<li>cannot be used by more than one person at the same time</li>
</ul>


<p>These characteristics don&#8217;t apply in the case of open data&#8230;</p>

<h2>Open Data: The Gift That Keeps On Giving</h2>

<p>An externality, or spillover effect, is a cost or benefit that is incurred by someone who is not involved in the trade. The price will not reflect these indirect social impacts. Pollution is an example of how external costs can lead to excessive production.</p>

<p><em>Network externalities</em> are a form of external benefit. Within a network the value of an adding an extra node or edge (e.g. person or friendship) is felt by every other part of the network. The Metrolink extension, for example, is not only of benefit to people in the new areas that can now use trams, but also to people in the existing areas that can now access new areas.</p>

<p>Network externalities occur in the case of open data because data is only informative when it is interpreted. The value of each datum increases with the volume of other data that it may be connected with as the context and range of analysis that are possible increases. Thus, data operates as a network. In deciding whether or not to open their data, <strong>private organisations will not consider the indirect benefits that their data will have to improve the quality of every other dataset</strong> and so will release less data than is socially optimal.</p>

<h2>Data As A Public Good</h2>

<p>A <em>public good</em> is one which is non-excludable (impossible to prevent people from using it) and non-rival (one person&#8217;s use doesn&#8217;t not reduce availability to another). The problem with these goods is that consumers can take advantage without contributing sufficiently to their creation. If too many people decide to <em>free-ride</em> then the private revenues won&#8217;t meet the private costs and the incentive to provide the good through the market will disappear.</p>

<p>Data is typically non-excludable. Although legislation may prohibit the buyer from sharing data it is, in many cases, practically unenforcable (as is apparent with music sharing, for example). Data is also non-rival. Your reading of this post does not prevent another person from reading it - indeed I don&#8217;t loose the ideas when I write them down - we can all enjoy them at the same time. <strong>Where data may be characterised as a public good, subject to the free-rider problem, there won&#8217;t be sufficient private incentives for production and distribution</strong>.</p>

<h2>Implications For Business &amp; Government</h2>

<p>So what does this economic analysis tell us?</p>

<ol>
<li>Technological change (particularly the increasing capacity for connecting and sharing data) will disrupt certain markets by undermining established closed-data business models;</li>
<li>Businesses that attempt to defend outdated business models by keeping data closed won&#8217;t be able to compete with an open alternatives (alternatives that they are encouraging by keeping their data closed);</li>
<li>It&#8217;s probably better for such businesses to open their data before a competitor does - they shouldn&#8217;t waste their current position of dominance;</li>
<li>In some cases, where the market fails completely, public intervention to fund the creation or provision of information will help to improve economic growth and social welfare;</li>
<li>In other cases there will be considerable <a href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2013/03/01/open-data-business-models">opportunities for private firms to innovate and capture the benefits of open data</a>.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winning Public Sector Contracts]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2011/11/30/winning-public-sector-contracts/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-30T13:11:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2011/11/30/winning-public-sector-contracts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was invited to provide some training at the <a href="http://www.socialsolutionsacademy.co.uk/"><acronym title="Social Solutions Academy">SSA</acronym></a>&#8217;s <a href="http://www.socialsolutionsacademy.co.uk/past-events/">Social Enterprise Action Day</a>.</p>

<p>One of the participants was kind enough to say:</p>

<blockquote><p>The &#8216;Winning public contracts&#8217; session very good, I was very impressed with content. The facilitator had undertaken some research about my social enterprise prior to the event and found a relevant funding opportunity. This was used as a case study during the session.</p><footer><strong>Rose Marley, Director</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.motiv.org.uk/'>Motiv CIC</a></cite></footer></blockquote>




<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15208098" width="427" height="356" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p> <div style="margin-bottom:5px"> <strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/robingower/winning-public-sector-contracts" title="Winning Public Sector Contracts" target="_blank">Winning Public Sector Contracts</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/robingower" target="_blank">robingower</a></strong> </div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Introduction to GNU-R]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2010/09/23/invitation-to-an-introduction-to-gnu-r-talk/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2010/09/23/invitation-to-an-introduction-to-gnu-r-talk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Manchester Free Software group has invited me to give a talk on&nbsp;<a target="_blank" href="http://www.r-project.org/">GNU-R</a>.</p>


<p><a target="_blank" href="http://libreplanet.org/wiki/Manchester/2010-10-19">http://libreplanet.org/wiki/<wbr></wbr>Manchester/2010-10-19</a></p>


<ul>
<li><a title="http://madlab.org.uk/" rel="nofollow" target="_blank" href="http://madlab.org.uk/">Madlab</a>&nbsp;(Manchester Digital Laboratory) Upstairs,&nbsp;36-40&nbsp;<a title="http://www.openstreetmap.org/?lat=53.484241&amp;lon=-2.236324&amp;zoom=18&amp;layers=B000FTF" rel="nofollow" target="_blank" href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/?lat=53.484241&amp;lon=-2.236324&amp;zoom=18&amp;layers=B000FTF">Edge Street</a>, Manchester, M4 1HN (between Thomas St and the Craft Centre, opposite A Bar Called Common).</li>
<li>Tuesday, 19th October 2010 (3rd Tuesday of the month) 19:00 - 20:30</li>
</ul>


<p>R is a system for statistical computation and graphics. &nbsp;At Infonomics we use R to handle much of our analytic work, particularly where there is repeated processing of data, complex statistical models, or requirements for data graphics that go beyond the limitations of spreadsheets. &nbsp;We&#8217;ve used it, for example, in the&nbsp;<a href="http://reports.infonomics.ltd.uk/">AutoReporter</a>.</p>


<p>The talk will provide: an introduction to R, discussion of when (and when not) to use R, and a guided tour of it&#8217;s capabilities with examples. &nbsp;It&#8217;s also a chance to learn about the secrets of some of our tools of the trade. We expect that audience will comprise those with a interest in data/ statistics, software and/ or visualisation.</p>


<p><a href="http://libreplanet.org/wiki/Manchester">Manchester Free Software</a>&nbsp;was formed in response to the growing need for a group based in the Manchester area that focuses on Free Software and GNU/Linux primarily, but also on issues such as Digital Restrictions Management and other issues which infringe on the freedoms of computer users.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing the AutoReporter]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2010/08/18/introducing-the-autoreporter/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2010/08/18/introducing-the-autoreporter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
<img class="left" src="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/images/post_images/robot3.png" title="AutoReporter" >
We&#8217;ve been busy developing some new products.&nbsp; We&#8217;re proud to announce the launch of the <a href="http://reports.infonomics.ltd.uk/">Auto-Reporter</a>.</p>


<p>The AutoReporter writes economic and statistical reports automatically.&nbsp; Our algorithm gathers, analyses, visualises, and interprets data.&nbsp; Because the process is robotic, it can rewrite whole reports with the tweak of a parameter.&nbsp; You can follow this link to read a <a href="http://reports.infonomics.ltd.uk/AutoReporter_v1.pdf">white paper describing the method</a>.&nbsp; You can may also want to download an <a href="http://reports.infonomics.ltd.uk/DownturnMcr.pdf">example report</a> (showing how the economic downturn will affect Manchester&#8217;s economy).</p>


<!--more-->


<p>There are a range of benefits:</p>


<ul>
    <li><strong>Don&rsquo;t repeat yourself</strong>: once a report is written it  may be regenerated many times, most importantly, every time new data is  made available &ndash; even years after the original draft;</li>
    <li><strong>Be transparent and credible</strong>: scripted reports  connect open data to decisions through analysis.  The evidence base, and  the logic used for interpretation is transparent and therefore  credible;</li>
    <li><strong>Don&rsquo;t worry about carrying errors forward</strong>: with  manually generated research, any mistakes made at the beginning are  costly as the error will be carried forward through subsequent stages.   Even after an error is discovered and corrected, subsequent tasks may need to  be redone (if they are based on the erroneous data).  With reproducible  research this process requires no costly repetition of manual tasks;</li>
    <li><strong>Benefit from lessons learned from other&rsquo;s mistakes</strong>:  a single report could be generated for multiple circumstances.  It&rsquo;s  likely that if your organisation values the report then others will too.   As a result, organisations may find that sharing ideas and techniques  will be of mutual benefit (notwithstanding issues of confidentiality or  competition);</li>
    <li><strong>Accuracy</strong>: The numbers and graphics reported are  accurate.  They&#8217;re calculated from source data each time the report is  run.  This avoids problems with mismatched versions of data and analysis  that often arise from inconsistent manual updates.</li>
    <li><strong>Power</strong>: Once a report has been written for one area,  it may be reproduced for others.  You&rsquo;ve written a report for your  borough and now you want one for each ward?  Fine!  Just change the  parameters on the report (data permitting) and you can generate the same  analysis (data tables and charts) for each neighbourhood.</li>
</ul>


<p>You can read a <a href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/portfolio_project/8">case study</a> about how Innovas Consulting employed this tool to produce 60+ tailored Enterprise Catalyst reports to schools in Yorkshire as part of an evaluation of enterprise activities in the region.</p>


<p>We&#8217;re keen to develop the technology further with our associates.&nbsp; We can prepare web applications that fit within your own websites, presented in with your own style and branding.&nbsp; This sort of technology will be valuable if you:</p>


<ul>
    <li>employ a common methodology to different clients,</li>
    <li>are keen to demonstrate credibility with reproducible research,</li>
    <li>regularly update your analysis with new data, and/or</li>
    <li>need to produce tailored reports or analyses in bulk (i.e. across many topics, indicators or areas).</li>
</ul>


<p>There are more exciting innovations in the pipeline so watch this space!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impact Evaluation Methods]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2010/04/27/impact-evaluation-methods/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2010/04/27/impact-evaluation-methods</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a brief review of impact evaluation methods.&nbsp; We consider the: <a href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file21900.pdf">Impact Evaluation Framework</a> for Regional Development Agencies, the <a href="http://www.offpat.info/Publication.aspx?ID=2536">English Partnerships Additionality Guide</a>, and the <a href="http://www.sroi-uk.org/component/option,com_docman/task,cat_view/gid,29/Itemid,38/">Social Return on Investment</a> method.<br />
<br />
We will demonstrate that:</p>


<ul>
    <li>it&#8217;s vital to realise that the results monitored by projects should not all count towards a measure of impact (as some of those results may have happened anyway);</li>
    <li>the method of calculating impact may be as interesting as the results of those calculations and, since interpretations may vary, transparency is vital to credibility;</li>
    <li>an appreciation of context is fundamental to successful impact evaluation.</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p><h2>From the easy-to-measure to the hard-to-prove </h2><br />
Each method builds upon the notion that, in order to evaluate the impact of public policy, we must consider outcomes rather than simply outputs.&nbsp; That is to say, that simply counting the results of activities (or even the level of activity) is not enough - we must investigate the consequences of those results.<br />
Each method translates gross outcomes to net outcomes.&nbsp; This is in response to the observation that not every observed benefit arises as a direct consequence of the intervention in question.&nbsp; Instead, by drawing on the notion of &#8216;additionally&#8217; we may begin to question what might have happened without the support.&nbsp; Impact evaluation then, takes us from the easy to measure to the hard to prove.&nbsp; Each method recommends that a &#8216;theory of change&#8217; be established so that the chain logic from inputs to impacts is explicit.<br />
This logic chain ought to cover the whole policy process from problem to solution.&nbsp; An understanding of the business case for investment is therefore absolutely vital to evaluation.<br />
<br />
<h2>Additional Impact</h2><br />
The methods do not include the same concepts and have markedly different recommendations on how impact ought to be calculated.&nbsp; Generally speaking, the following elements are considered:</p>


<ul>
    <li>Deadweight (aka the reference case): those benefits that might have occurred anyway (not to be confused with &#8216;deadweight loss&#8217; that refers to the loss of consumer and producer surplus that occurs when a tax reduces the quantity of trade).</li>
    <li>Displacement: the increase in benefits that is offset by a reduction elsewhere (e.g. where a business grows at the expense of competitors there is no net benefit to the economy).</li>
    <li>Substitution: the possibility that people have transferred existing activity in order to benefit from the policy under evaluation (rather than through an existing route to the outcome).</li>
    <li>Multipliers: the indirect, or &#8216;second-round&#8217; benefits that arise as a consequence of the direct benefits.</li>
    <li>Leakage: the possibility that some benefits accrue to people who are not part of the target group.</li>
    <li>Leverage: where the intervention induces other stakeholders to contribute additional expenditure (or reduce that expenditure).</li>
    <li>Unintended effects: benefits or costs that were not anticipated.</li>
    <li>Attribution: those results that were not the direct result of the policy intervention under question - i.e. those results for which other groups were responsible.</li>
</ul>


<p>These factors are usually treated as ratios that are applied to the gross value in order to calculate a net value.<br />
The English Parnterships Additionality Guide calculates net impact as the difference between a set of intervention options and a reference case (a counter-factual hypothesis of what would have happened otherwise) where measures of leakage, displace, substation and multipliers are applied to both the invention option and the reference case.<br />
The <acronym title="Social Return on Investment">SROI</acronym> method requires that outputs or outcomes are converted into sterling by drawing upon financial proxies that may be used to translate intangible social benefits into a standard unit of account.&nbsp; These are commonly the unit costs of alternate interventions or estimates from hedonic pricing models.</p>


<p><br />
<h2>Theory into Practice</h2><br />
There is a degree of overlap between these concepts.&nbsp; Substitution may be also appear as displacement (was the alternative activity public or private?) or deadweight (is it fair to say that the benefits would have happened anyway if that result was attributable to another policy?).&nbsp; Attribution and deadweight may also be seen to overlap (again, was the result achieved by another policy?).<br />
Furthermore, linear models that combine these factors may over-simplify the complexity of the underlying situation.&nbsp; For example, it will be difficult to attribute responsibility for the benefits separately to each of those involved where two partners had to work in concert to achieve the outcome (in such a case the benefit might be counted twice - once for each partner).&nbsp; It might also be argued that multipliers ought to be applied to substitution and displacement effects (which in turn will also have second round effects).&nbsp; In reality the chain of causality will be non-linear, and may even be cyclical, with the outcomes from one stage contributing to those in another.&nbsp; In this situation it becomes very difficult to avoid counting outcomes more than once.<br />
This complexity is particularly relevant when conducting Social Return on Investment analysis as this approach to impact evaluation accounts for the social value that arises from economic value.&nbsp; For example, where an unemployed person gains employment there is a obvious economic benefit to that individual (immediately the salary and, over the longer-term, career opportunities will improve) and also social benefits such as savings on transfer payments (as the individual will stop claiming Job Seekers Allowance and start making income tax contributions).&nbsp; The rule of thumb suggested in the SROI guidance is that, to avoid double-counting, one should consider: &quot;am I counting the same value, for the same stakeholder, twice?&quot;.<br />
<br />
<h2>Impact is in the eye of the stakeholder</h2><br />
Context and perspective are vital to the interpretation of impact.&nbsp; Since no policy operates in a vacuum, and there will usually be related programmes of intervention, evaluators must consider how the policy interacts with other forms of public support as well as how it impacts the targeted beneficiaries.<br />
Consideration of each stakeholder is designed into the SROI method.&nbsp; Indeed this method essentially advocates that the impact on each stakeholder be considered in parallel with separate impact calculations being made for each.&nbsp; The discussion above highlights the difficulty evaluators face in distinguishing between stakeholders.&nbsp; Indeed it&#8217;s not clear how collective benefits (those that may be said to be more than the sum of the individual outcomes - the inward investment that a town enjoys as a result of a better skilled workforce is more than simply the aggregate productivity increase among trainees) ought to be modelled, if at all, although a general &quot;state&quot; stakeholder may be called-upon as a catch-all for those benefits enjoyed by society.<br />
The <acronym title="Impact Evaluation Framework">IEF</acronym> method incorporates external (i.e. non-<acronym title="Regional Development Agency">RDA</acronym>) stakeholders under the assessment of &quot;strategic added value&quot;.&nbsp; This models the impact that the RDA has upon partners in terms of:</p>


<ul>
    <li>Strategic leadership &amp; catalyst: Articulating and communicating regional development needs, opportunities and solutions to partners and stakeholders in the region and elsewhere;</li>
    <li>Strategic influence: Carrying out or stimulating activity that defines the distinctive roles of partners, gets them to commit to shared strategic objectives and to behave and allocate their funds accordingly;</li>
    <li>Leverage: Providing financial and other incentives to mobilise partner and stakeholder resources &ndash; equipment, people as well as funding</li>
    <li>Synergy: Using organisational capacity, knowledge and expertise to improve information exchange and knowledge transfer and coordination and/or integration of the design and delivery of interventions between partners;</li>
    <li>Engagement: Setting up the mechanisms and incentives for more effective and deliberative engagement of stakeholders in the design and delivery of regional and sub-regional priorities and programmes.</li>
</ul>


<p>By comparison with the SROI method, the notion of Strategic Added Value is less mathematical.&nbsp; <acronym title="Strategic Added Value">SAV</acronym> does not model the impact on each stakeholder explicitly and instead takes a &#8216;soft-systems&#8217; approach where the focus is on organisational structures and processes rather than on measuring benefits accrued.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p><h2>Summary</h2><br />
The discussion of factors of additionality demonstrates that counting gross outputs will not provide a fair perspective and that outcomes must be considered when evaluating impact.</p>


<p>In practice these factors may overlap and combine.&nbsp; An understanding of context is vital to disentangle the interplay of these factors.</p>


<p>These factors will vary again when viewed from the perspective of different stakeholders.&nbsp; A balanced impact evaluation will take this into account.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Statisticians are sexy!]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2009/09/14/statisticians-are-sexy/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2009/09/14/statisticians-are-sexy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Plain-speaking Economics professor-cum-googler <a href="http://people.ischool.berkeley.edu/~hal/">Hal R. Varian</a> believes that the &quot;sexy job in the next ten years will be statisticians&quot;.</p>


<!--more-->


<p>He reasons that, since data is cheap (often free) and ubiquitous, complimentary skills - to understand data and extract value from it - are highly valuable.&nbsp; By contrast, attention is scarce on the internet.&nbsp; &quot;The ability to take data&mdash;to be able to understand it, to process it, to extract value from it, to visualize it, to communicate it&mdash;that&rsquo;s going to be a hugely important skill in the next decades&quot;.</p>


<p>You can read the full text of the article, or listen to a podcast at <a href="http://www.mckinseyquarterly.com/Hal_Varian_on_how_the_Web_challenges_managers_2286">The McKinsey Quarterly</a>.</p>


<p>We agree with Prof Varian.&nbsp; We believe that our capacity for converting data into information makes Infonomics an attractive prospect for our clients.&nbsp; We&#8217;ll leave the reader to decide whether or not this plays a role in the physical attractiveness of our consultants - after all <a href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2008/12/19/lies-damn-lies-and-your-evidence-base/">correlation doesn&#8217;t always imply correlation</a>!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The public has spoken - exploring e-petitions]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2009/04/24/the-public-has-spoken-exploring-e-petitions/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2009/04/24/the-public-has-spoken-exploring-e-petitions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Petitions for Action - Verbs used in e-petitions</h2>


<p><img src="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/images/post_images/p-verbs-manyeyes.preview.png" title="&#34;Petitions for action - verbs used in e-petitions&#34;" alt="&#34;Petitions for action - verbs used in e-petitions&#34;"></p>

<!--more-->


<h3>E-Petitions as an alternative to consultation</h3>


<p>The <a href="http://petitions.number10.gov.uk/">e-petitions on Number10.gov</a> are fascinating.&nbsp; As we&#8217;ve come to expect from <a target="_blank" href="http://www.mysociety.org/projects/">mySociety projects</a>, &quot;the e-petition system has been designed to be transparent and trustworthy&quot;.&nbsp; The petitions provide an unbiased perspective on the view of the UK public and a <strong>valuable evidence base</strong> for policy makers.</p>


<p>Although the feedback is free from the constraints of normal consultation (where the questions may be&nbsp; framed unintentionally) it is unstructured and this makes it difficult for policy makers to use.&nbsp; Hope is not lost however, help is at hand in the form of <strong>semantic analysis</strong>.</p>


<h3>Extract information from e-petition data with semantic analysis</h3>


<p>The image above was constructed by annotating the text in the titles of the petitions.&nbsp; We searched for verbs and extracted the pruned form of those verbs (e.g. &quot;increasing&quot; becomes &quot;increase&quot;) along with the number of signatures to the petition where the verbs were found.&nbsp; The words are weighted according to the total number of signatures.&nbsp; The visualisation was prepared using IBM&#8217;s <a href="http://manyeyes.alphaworks.ibm.com/manyeyes/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">Many Eyes</a> (note that data submitted to Many Eyes can be viewed by anyone on the internet).</p>


<p>Annotation can also be used to find organisations and places.&nbsp; The results of those analyses are presented in the lists below.</p>


<table cellspacing="1" cellpadding="1" border="0">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td>
            <h3>Top 10 Organisations in UK&nbsp;petitions</h3>
            </td>
            <td>
            <h3>Top 10 Places in UK petitions</h3>
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>
            <ol>
                <li>United Nations (17323)</li>
                <li>Service of Her Majesty (15648)</li>
                <li>Royal Bank of Scotland (3131)</li>
                <li>Government (3668)</li>
                <li>National Health Service (2274)</li>
                <li>Royal Infirmary (2084)</li>
                <li>Yorkshire Television (1668)</li>
                <li>UK Emergency Services (1601)</li>
                <li>European Union (1716)</li>
                <li>GCHQ (980)</li>
            </ol>
            </td>
            <td>
            <ol>
                <li>England (23171)</li>
                <li>Bletchley Park (20197)</li>
                <li>London (17084)</li>
                <li>Cherry Lane (12450)</li>
                <li>UK (17808)</li>
                <li>Northern Ireland (5188)</li>
                <li>Richmond (3454)</li>
                <li>Memorial Wall (3372)</li>
                <li>Scotland (2187)</li>
                <li>Leeds (1668)</li>
            </ol>
            </td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>


<h3>Beware of junk data</h3>


<p>Although the openness of e-petitions is a virtue, it does mean that there is a lot of junk to sift through.&nbsp; Only 1.3% of open petitions have enough signatures (at least 200) to qualify for consideration by Government.&nbsp; Clearly the other petitions have some value even though they may be minority concerns.&nbsp; Indeed the number of signatures is not a perfect measure of quality or relevance.</p>


<h3>Using the evidence in policy development</h3>


<ul>
    <li><strong>Keep track of petitions that are made regarding your organisation or place</strong>.&nbsp; We were able to identify 352 references to organisations, 36 of which were Councils.&nbsp; <a href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/contact">Get in touch</a> for some tips on monitoring the web for references to your organisation.</li>
    <li><strong>Identify issues that are relevant to your objectives</strong>.&nbsp; We recently employed <a href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/portfolio_project/4">semantic analysis that helped Investor Developers at the East Midlands Development Agency forecast demand for support by extracting information from visit reports</a>.&nbsp; Petitions provide evidence of needs (or at least demands) and issues (learn from others mistakes).</li>
    <li><strong>Gauge public opinions on existing policy</strong>.&nbsp; Congestion-charging, War, Bank-bailouts - they&#8217;re all subjects of petitions.&nbsp; While many of the petitions express peoples&#8217; feelings on these issues there are others that contain concrete suggestions for policy improvements.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[People Managed Places]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2009/02/13/people-managed-places/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2009/02/13/people-managed-places</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/viewContentItem.do?contentType=Article&amp;contentId=1748140">People-managed Place</a> is an idea introduced by Robin Gower in an article published by the Journal of Place Management and Development.</p>


<p>The &quot;place management problem&quot; arises because:</p>


<ul>
    <li><strong>Together we are stronger (or, that cooperative outcomes often beat competitive ones)</strong>: the tragedy of the commons and existence of social externalities in our environment;</li>
    <li><strong>Diverse communities don&#8217;t tend to share places very well</strong>: non-cooperative game theory suggests that we won&#8217;t share spontaneously;</li>
    <li><strong>Active place management is inherently difficult</strong>: because of the complexity involved Planners are at risk of becoming part of the problem!</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p>The article warns that if opt to &quot;do-nothing&quot; then we face the <strong>risk of inaction &ndash; standardised places</strong> where developers and national retail chains unwittingly reduce our metropolitan areas to a network of <a href="http://www.neweconomics.org/gen/clonetownbritainnewsthefightback200306.aspx">clone-towns</a>.&nbsp; The proposed range of solutions are <strong>bottom-up rather than top-down</strong> and focus on <strong>users not functions</strong>:</p>


<ul>
    <li><strong>Inter-dependence through trade</strong> (the butcher needs the baker and vice versa)</li>
    <li><strong>Agglomeration Economies &amp; Business Clusters</strong> (industrial communities)</li>
    <li>the <strong>Sidewalk Ballet</strong> (the eyes of fellow pedestrians make streets safer than CCTV cameras)</li>
</ul>


<p>Each of these examples demonstrates that place management ought not attempt to zone and plan but to empower individuals and let places evolve organically.&nbsp;  Place managers can deal with the complex socio-economic problems of place by facilitating and regulating a stronger civil society.&nbsp;  The article refers to the similar advice suggested by other authors (such as the <a href="http://www.ceu-ectp.org/e/athens/">New Athens Charter</a>, the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principles_of_Intelligent_Urbanism">principles of intelligent urbanism</a> and Camilo Sitte&#8217;s belief that plazas and squares are civic rooms that ought to be left open) and provides a brief summary of the relevant UK legislation. &nbsp; The analysis leads me to make the following recommendations:</p>


<ul>
    <li><strong>Start with current place users</strong>: i.e. not place functions</li>
    <li><strong>Consider potential place users</strong>: to ensure dynamic sustainability</li>
    <li><strong>Define place-based rights &amp; responsibilities</strong>: to protect place uses (e.g. <a href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/en/CrimeJusticeAndTheLaw/CrimePrevention/DG_4001652">Anti-Social Behaviour Orders</a> or <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emissions_trading">tradeable pollution permits</a>)</li>
    <li><strong>Encourage collaboration</strong>: through, for example, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_improvement_district">Business Improvement Districts</a></li>
    <li><strong>Cross boundaries and work with your neighbours</strong>: zero-sum games are the bane of place-management policy - use partnerships to communicate and negotiate</li>
    <li><strong>Place Making/ Leadership - internalise externalities</strong>: place-manager must make place-users aware of the social costs and benefits (publicise planning gains and declare what supplementary business rates are spent on).</li>
</ul>


<p class="rteleft">Michael Heller has coined a phrase that describes the problem of multiple and complex claims on a common resource: The Tragedy of the Anti-Commons.&nbsp;  In the video below Professor Heller discusses his book, <a href="http://www.gridlockeconomy.com/">The Gridlock Economy</a>.</p>


<p class="rtecenter"><object width="425" height="344">
<param value="http://www.youtube.com/v/9n89Ec3DFtk&amp;color1=0xb1b1b1&amp;color2=0xcfcfcf&amp;hl=en&amp;fs=1" name="movie" />
<param value="true" name="allowFullScreen" /><embed width="425" height="344" allowfullscreen="true" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" src="http://www.youtube.com/v/9n89Ec3DFtk&amp;color1=0xb1b1b1&amp;color2=0xcfcfcf&amp;hl=en&amp;fs=1"></embed></object></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lies, Damn Lies, and your Evidence Base]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2008/12/19/lies-damn-lies-and-your-evidence-base/"/>
    <updated>2008-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2008/12/19/lies-damn-lies-and-your-evidence-base</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>People can come up with statistics to prove anything, Kent.  40% of all people know that</p><footer><strong>Homer</strong> <cite>The Simpsons</cite></footer></blockquote>


<p>Statistics are confusing.  Any science that spawns phrase like &quot;the presence of heteroskedasticty indicates that the disturbances are non-spherical&quot; is bound to be mis-interpreted at some stage.  Of course the same might be said of many technical disciplines but the fact that I don&#8217;t understand the ins-and-outs of neuro-science presents me with little difficulty in my daily life.  Statistics on the other hand, are everywhere!  The following tips are aimed as the non-statisticians who&#8217;s work requires them to interpret statistics.  </p>


<!--more-->


<p><img title="... okay, but because you said that, we're breaking up." boyfriend="" xkcd.com="" alt="" src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/boyfriend.png" /></p>

<p>I&#8217;m particularly thinking of policy makers who are faced with the task of gathering an evidence base to guide their strategies and actions.  These warnings encourage a healthy degree of scepticism and give you a better idea of what questions to ask of your research.  Before we begin, it&#8217;s worth <strong>defining the word <em>statistic</em></strong>.  When we&#8217;re describing something quantitatively we refer to parameters about the population; for example: &quot;there are 10 cars on my street&quot;.  When we don&#8217;t know about the whole population (e.g. my neighbourhood), we have to look at a sample (e.g. my street).  We can estimate the population parameter from the sample (e.g. there are 10 cars on my street, and 10 streets in my neighbourhood, therefore I estimate that there are 100 cars in my neighbourhood).  The sample statistic (cars in street) used to estimate the population parameter (cars in neighbourhood).
</p>


<ol><img class="right" src="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/images/post_images/confused-smaller.jpg">
    <li><strong>Statistics never prove anything!</strong>  Let&#8217;s be up-front about this.  Statistics are not the truth but they can tell you about lies.  Statistical inference is a process of elimination.  I don&#8217;t prove my theory, I just disprove everything else!  Or as Sherlock Holmes would have it: &quot;when you have eliminated the impossible, whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth&quot;.  In reality, it&#8217;s impractical to eliminate <i>all</i> impossibilities.  Our first health warning then, is not to take anything as given: question everything!</li>
    <li><strong>What&#8217;s the point in statistics?</strong>  Because statistics are estimates that draw on a limited view of reality there is a risk that they&#8217;ll give the wrong answer.  This is known as sampling error.  When you see a statistic presented you&#8217;re typically looking at what&#8217;s called a point estimate.  This is the most probable value that we think the underlying population parameter will take - our best guess.  Good statisticians provide confidence intervals along with their point estimates.  These intervals give the range of values we expect the parameter could actually take.  In order to really understand a statistic you ought to know range of possibilities.  Technically the full range is infinite, but statisticians tend to allow some margin of error - such as a 5% tolerance for inaccuracy - giving them interval that contains the actual value 95% of the time.</li>
    <li><strong>Expect the unexpected!</strong>  A corollary of the second point is that statistics will be wrong 5% of the time.  If your evidence base quotes 20 statistics then you can expect one of them to be wrong.  This further illustrates the importance of the first point.  The question is how rare is rare?  Statisticians call the tolerance for inaccuracy (e.g. 5%) a type one error (excessive trust) - it is the likelihood that they&#8217;ll erroneously reject the truth.  The alternative is to ask &quot;how much inaccuracy must I tolerate to accept this statistic?&quot; which leads to the second type of error: failing to reject a falsehood (excessive scepticism).  Health warning: You can&#8217;t expect to be right all the time, but it helps to know how often, on balance, you&#8217;ll be wrong.</li>
    <li><strong>Bigger populations do not always need bigger samples!</strong>  This is a common, and understandable, misconception.  Population size alone cannot tell you how big a sample you&#8217;ll need to consider (e.g. when planning a survey).  It&#8217;s also important to ask: &quot;how variable is the population?&quot;.  Suppose I want to know the most common car colour.  If everyone drives the same colour car then, no matter how many cars there are, I&#8217;ll only need to ask 1 driver.  Of course you won&#8217;t typically know the population variance (a measure of variety - the dispersal around the mean) in advance of your fieldwork.  A practical approach is to look for secondary data which you can use to estimate the population variance.  For modestly-sized research projects, a useful rule of thumb is that diminishing returns tend to set-in as the sample size increases above 30.  You ought to have at least 30 results for each sub-group or segment you wish to analyse or contrast (bear in mind that once you&#8217;ve cut out the &quot;don&#8217;t know&quot;&#8217;s you&#8217;ll probably need more than 30 respondents to achieve 30 responses).  Obviously for larger investigation - especially in novel topic areas where the secondary evidence is missing - there is rationale for larger sample sizes.</li>
</ol>


<p>For further information I recommend <a href="www.bbc.co.uk/moreorless">BBC Radio 4&#8217;s More or Less</a> programme on which Tim Harford (the Undercover Economist) provides a sanity-check to the barrage of statistics quoted by the media: <quote>&quot;More or Less is devoted to the powerful, sometimes beautiful, often abused but ever ubiquitous world of numbers&quot;.</quote></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Information Markets as a Tool for Forecasting and Policy Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2008/08/04/why-should-government-policy-makers-know-about-information-markets/"/>
    <updated>2008-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/blog/2008/08/04/why-should-government-policy-makers-know-about-information-markets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Introducing information markets</h2>


<p><img class="left" src="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/news/images/post_images/cards_smaller.jpg" title="Prediction Markets: a safe bet for forecasters" >This article explains how information markets can assist policy developers by estimating predictions and making decisions.  Economists have long been convinced by the power of markets to allocate resources efficiently.  Markets are, so the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Efficient_market_hypothesis">theory</a> goes, able to <strong>condense all available information about a particular product into one measure</strong>: the price.  But what if the commodity you&#8217;re trading is itself information?  Information markets are designed to put the power of trade to work on information: predictions, decisions and estimates more generally. </p>


<!--more-->


<p>The markets operate like a betting shop.  Gamblers bid on the expected outcomes of an event - the 2008, 4th Quarter Employment rate for example - and the bookmaker pays out to those who judged the value successfully.  Justin Wolfers&#8217; <em>Political Prediction Markets: a Webcast for the Uninitiated</em> provides an inspiring introduction to the topic.  You can find a link to the webcast over at the <a href="http://freakonomics.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/07/01/political-prediction-markets-webcast-for-the-uninitiated/">Freakonomics blog</a>.&nbsp;   To summarise, information markets can:</p>


<ul>
    <li>summarise all available information</li>
    <li>make accurate predictions</li>
    <li>respond rapidly to news</li>
    <li>provide an incentive for information discovery</li>
    <li>encourage truth revelation</li>
</ul>


<p>Information markets are even robust to manipulation attempts because traders can profit from betting against the lies espoused by manipulators.</p>


<h2>Potential application of information markets for government</h2>


<p>Information markets could be used to provide answers to the questions of policy development. Information markets can provide predictions for policy research and make decisions to guide strategy and implementation.</p>


<h3>Prediction Markets as a Research Intelligence tool</h3>


<p>Forecasting is an obvious application.  Information markets can <strong>summarise the implications of an evidence base in a meaningful way</strong>: indeed the only limit to the practical applicability of the results is the designer&#8217;s imagination.  With a large enough body of traders, the market can provide a <strong>continuously updated and accurate reflection of all available intelligence</strong>.  A dynamically adjusted indication of labour market indicators for example.  With the appropriate incentives, <strong>the market will induce traders to gather new evidence on the designer&#8217;s behalf</strong>.  Experts may be sufficiently motivated by the credibility that their company can earn from accurate prediction.  Kudos points translate in contract awards.  Ask five economists the same question, you will get six different answers, but if you ask them to bet on their answers you can only get one response.  In fact, as Justin Wolfers explains above, the results from <strong>information markets are more accurate than expert surveys</strong>.</p>


<h3>Decision Markets as a Policy Choice tool</h3>


<p>What if we apply decision markets to the questions of policy development?  In 2000, Robin Hanson wrote a <a href="http://hanson.gmu.edu/futarchy.html">manifesto describing a new form of government</a>. <quote>In &quot;futarchy,&quot; we would vote on values, but bet on beliefs. Elected representatives would formally define and manage an after-the-fact measurement of national welfare, while market speculators would say which policies they expect to raise national welfare.  The basic rule of government would be: <strong>When a betting market clearly estimates that a proposed policy would increase expected national welfare, that proposal becomes law. </strong></quote>  Futarky is a strong governance model because of two attributes.  Follow the links to understand why these attributes are so desirable:</p>


<ul>
    <li>Pursuit of welfare that includes both productivity and happiness - Nowadays the first is a given.  If you aren&#8217;t convinced that well-being is important, then you obviously haven&#8217;t heard the evidence from <a href="http://cep.lse.ac.uk/layard/">Richard Layard</a>&#8217;s study into this &quot;new science &quot;.  As he points out: <quote>So here we are as a society: no happier than fifty years ago.  Yet every group in society is richer, and most are healthier&#8230;  Through science, absolute material scarcity has been conquered in the West, and we need to think hard about what would now constitute progress.</quote></li>
    <li>Checks and balances - Watch the video below to see Paul Collier explain why this is such an important aspect of modern social democracy.  Source:  Paul Collier - 4 ways to improve the lives of the &quot;bottom billion&quot;, <a href="http://www.ted.com">TED Talks</a>.<object height="326" width="446">
    <param name="movie" value="http://video.ted.com/assets/player/swf/EmbedPlayer.swf" />
    <param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" />
    <param name="wmode" value="transparent" />
    <param name="bgColor" value="#ffffff" />
    <param name="flashvars" value="vu=http://video.ted.com/talks/embed/PaulCollier_2008-embed_high.flv&amp;su=http://images.ted.com/images/ted/tedindex/embed-posters/PaulCollier-2008.embed_thumbnail.jpg&amp;vw=432&amp;vh=240&amp;ap=0&amp;ti=270" /><embed height="326" width="446" src="http://video.ted.com/assets/player/swf/EmbedPlayer.swf" pluginspace="http://www.macromedia.com/go/getflashplayer" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" wmode="transparent" bgcolor="#ffffff" allowfullscreen="true" flashvars="vu=http://video.ted.com/talks/embed/PaulCollier_2008-embed_high.flv&amp;su=http://images.ted.com/images/ted/tedindex/embed-posters/PaulCollier-2008.embed_thumbnail.jpg&amp;vw=432&amp;vh=240&amp;ap=0&amp;ti=270"></embed></object></li>
</ul>


<h2>A health warning</h2>


<p>While it is tempting to launch straight into information markets, the pragmatic policy-maker ought to first consider some of the caveats.  Like any other market, information markets are subject to market failures.  They <strong>will fail if there are too few participants</strong> - like a traditional commodity the market fails in the presence of monopoly power.  Information markets must be designed carefully (particularly where a market-maker is used) so that the rules of trade do not bestow an unfair disadvantage that distorts the incentives for trade.  Just as information markets can be distorted by robotic market-makers, human experts may have <strong>unfair access to relevant knowledge</strong>.  Information asymmetries make it difficult for traders to judge the qualities of the different options facing them and may, in extreme cases, cause the markets to collapse completely.  This is a critical issue when choosing who will participate and how they are engaged.  Furthermore, information markets <strong>fail if nobody has any useful information</strong>!  They can be used to illicit information from people who wouldn&#8217;t ordinarily share their models or data.    For more information on how to design and employ information markets to solve your policy development problems, please get in <a href="http://infonomics.ltd.uk/contact">contact</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
